Hello!
Do you know who this person is?
I don't.
Would you like me to tell you a story?
Yes, I'd like that very much.
Okay honey, let's go.
Just one minute, he's going to tell us a story.
This is a story of bravery,
vengeance
and justice.
It began a long time ago,
in the prosperous kingdom of Ajeromi.
Have you seen yourselves?
After several warnings, you refused to listen!
Now you have to bear the consequences of your actions.
That's how it should be.
Is it not so?
It is so!
You have done the unthinkable
now you will pay for it.
Ajeromi is not responsible for your deaths!
It's not us.
Do you understand? Ajeromi is not responsible for your deaths!
It's your act of stealing that is getting you killed.
Is it not so?
It is so…
Just imagine what they stole…
look at it.
Ajipejo! (Snake charmer)
Yes!
Do your job.
(Incantations)
Come out!
Ajeromi kingdom was known for her strict punishment
for offences committed against the land
And of them all, stealing was the most despicable,
even petty stealing.
And the punishment for it, the gravest.
When our story begins, Ajeromi kingdom is
celebrating the coronation of a new king.
King Adegbite.
You are now King over everything.
We will take you to all of them,
where you will prostrate to them for the last time ever!
To finish his coronation rights, the king must pay
homage to the existing factions in his kingdom.
The Ifa Diviners.
The witches.
Adegbite, the son of Tadenikaro,
Congratulations on the ascension of the throne.
Henceforth, you have become the king of witches.
You have become the King of sorcerers!
Adegbite, you have also become the king of all spirit mothers.
You have become king over all the deadly
wizards who kill without warning.
[Wizard chant]
Pay homage to the King!
All hail the King!
The Sango Oracle
[Sango chants]
Where is my food? Where is my food?
The Spiritual Forces.
Now that the King has paid homage, let us do the same.
All hail the King!
And the heavenly beings you
know as masquerades.
King Adegbite, may you reign long.
Amen
May rats cry like rats
May birds cry like birds
Amen
And may humans behave like humans
Amen....
The King was king over all. Loved by everything
he watched over, and untouched by none.
That’s enough.
Hail the King
My King.
King Adegbite,
Son of Tadenikaro,
the Prince who has now become the King!
May your reign be long
Amen
May you live long
I greet everyone of you here today, may we experience peace always.
Amen
May we will leave wealth for our children.
Isn’t it a glorious one for us?
It is!
My King will address you all...
My King.
All Hail the King
High Chief, may you live long.
Amen
May you all prosper in all you do
Villagers!
(Cheering)
I greet you all!
We greet you too!
This celebration is for all of us!
Yes
I greet all the chiefs
(Cheering)
I greet all the Royal Fathers seated, thank you for rejoicing with me!
May we have more of such happy celebration.
Amen
While I was in seclusion, I heard everything going on out here.
In particular, I heard about the activities of the Royal families…
(Hailing the King)
thank you all for standing by me.
There was a song I was told you sang while I was in seclusion.
Please, can you sing the song for me now?
They are always ready.
(Women singing and dancing)
We got the crown, above all others.
That is fine, thank you so much.
Today is not the day for much banter, let’s keep rejoicing and dancing.
Amen..
And we will continue to rejoice.
Where are the King’s masquerades?
Potash is a very rare kind of stone.
Oh yes
Salt is a very different kind of sand
You are right!
I have witnessed many coronations
but Adegbite's is different.
Why won't it be so?
I have witnessed more of such in the past,
Is it because he gave us horses and gifts?
This might be because you’re closer to his village.
But to be honest, these are a lot of gifts.
Only a greedy person will say
this is not a lot of gifts.
But Ajeromi Kingdom had a brewing crisis.
A group of bandits terrorized the land,
plundered the reserves, and carted away
valuables, and people into slavery.
This band of robbers was led by a
powerful man named Agesinkole.
Can't you see we are royalty?
Kneel down!
[Agesinkole group slang]
Seize the royal beads on their necks.
Sit there!
Take their slaves and properties to my palace.
[Kings whimpering]
Quiet! My Lord wants to speak!
I have no desires to kill anyone today,
but I want to send a warning message.
You, leave that place!
[Kings crying.]
Take everything to my palace!
Move! Move!!
Why are you silent? Who is the person?
Erm... My King,
no one really know who he is!
They claimed he suddenly appeared to them in the bush.
In fact, this person assaulted one of the Kings!
I ask again, who is this notorious and audacious person!
Who?
M.. My King.
They call him Agesinkole!
Agesinkole?
I am the one.
I am the untouchable one
I am invincible and as slippery as an eel
Do not underestimate my power.
I cannot be captured by your petty armaments
Look here this man, this is bigger than you!
You are sick!
May you and your ancestors not prosper!
How dare you brag before me, Adegbite!
Adegbite who hates empty words.
Who defeated rebels and evil ones.
I, the son of Tadenikaro who never runs from any fight.
I am always ready for war
Because my Father’s spirit leads me everytime
I need you to answer my questions!
Why did you ambush and steal from the Kings who came for my coronation?
This is just the beginning. In fact, I am yet to start,
I just showed you a little and Ajeromi is afraid.
If I throw the staff in my hand, it will destroy everyone dear to you.
You are just bluffing! You cannot do a thing!
No amount of saliva can ever make an ocean
I command you and your evil tricks to perish with you
The gods of the world, my ancesstors, take him!
Abomination!
I will not die.
And sickness will not befall me.
May today's death not be my portion.
May sickness of the day not be my portion.
This dream has a lot meanings.
The queen's unusual sleeping position
greatly troubled the king,
and it was a source for concern.
My King, I have told you to stop asking that question…
I already told you that some matters are for specific periods.
Go and see your Chiefs and do what you need to do for your people.
We will talk about our personal issues when the time is right.
I have heard you, but I
My King, when there are multiple problems, we handle the important ones first.
The issue facing the village right now is more important than
the issue between us.
My King, go attend to the chiefs.
Is that what you want it?
Yes.
Okay. No Problem.
My King…
Hello.
[Hunter chanting]
Ha, Alari
Rise, rise… It's been a while.
How are your children?
We are all well, thank you.
Hmm... Alari,
this burden for two that has become all yours, may it be easy for you.
Amen
God will support you.
Alari, It is true what they say that
when the head of a house dies,
the house may become chaotic.
If the mother dies, the children may disorderly.
But whoever has the support of the almighty, is covered.
May he help you carry your burden
Amen
Unfortunately, today isn’t a good day in the forest,
but let’s do this…
This is what ogun provided today, you can have it and make some delicacy.
Really! Thank you so much
Hello.
May the god of iron be with you.
Thank you so much, may you become more successful.
Amen
Thank you so much.
Mother.
Ha, this is Alari!
It is certain I will be fortunate today!
Oh, mother!
It's being a while
Yes mother, I went on a short journey
Really?
I came back two nights ago.
How are the children?
They are with my mother on a holiday.
That is good, you can also seize the opportunity to rest
...true.
Please mother, when Oguntade returns,
thank him on my behalf,
he gave me a whole Guinea Fowl this morning
Really?
You should also thank the hunter's wife.
oh, I didn’t know...
save it
What is it?
Ariyibi.
Are you surprised by Ariyibi's actions?
She has inherited bitterness from her people
Its fine. So, what can I help you with ma?
oh please, don’t bother.
Hello! Who is home?
Aríyíbí! Aríyíbí! I’m back
What is it? Why are you shouting my name?
Ariyibi.
Why are you always ready for a fight?
Have I offended you just now?
Why is your face like this?
My dear Ariyibi
[Praises Aríyíbí]
Why are you upset with me?
I would have really loved to continue praising you,
but right now, I am hungry.
I need you to arrange my food and some bath water
We have no food at home
We have no food at home?
What happened to the grass cutter soup you cooked yesterday?
I already washed it away.
You washed it away?
Yes
Was it tainted with a rat’s urine?
No, I just washed it away.
Ha!
Please, kindly show me the Elephant you brought home.
What Elephant?
No Elephant, yet you gave out a whole Guinea fowl?
Isn't that so?
For you to give such away, then you must have an elephant to bring home.
Àdùnní…
What has the guinea fowl I gave out got
to do with the soup you washed away?
The great philanthropist! When hunger tortures you, you will understand
continue to chat with the wall
Aríyíbí! Aríyíbí!
You want the god of Iron to...
I have made a terrible mistake marrying you
While the king worried about his wife's predicament,
Agesinkole's reign of terror spread
further into Ajeromi kingdom.
The kingdom was brought to it's knees,
and help was sought from far and wide,
for a champion to defeat the
menace of this king of thieves.
While the king worried about his wife's predicament, Agesinkole's reign of terror spread further into Ajeromi kingdom.
It will not be well with everyone of you.
First the association of hunters led
by oguntade was summoned.
The local hunters always have the
support of Ogun, the god of Iron.
Look, if you all gather and attack him, he will be dead!
What is the use of the sticks you all carry that you call guns
Head Hunter? Is this why you brought us here? Can we go home?
- Which home are you talking about?
- Our homes
Which home?
We are talking about a notorious criminal here and you hunters can't seem to do anything about it.
Isn’t a hunter superior to a thief?
Look...
What are we looking at Chief? What is there to See?
We can't be hunters and not be bold enough to speak the truth.
Look...
I don’t mean to sound offensive but we are hunters not hired killers!
Oh Yes!
Hunters, am I correct?
Animals will die, human will live.
Did you hear them Chiefs?
They said animals will die, human will live!
Was that what they said?
Exactly what they said!
Listen well to me Chief, you have High
Chiefs in the Village who are warriors…
the ones you have made Warrior.
Send them on this mission to kill for you.
It is the duty handed to them by their fathers.
Yes!
We are mere hunters!
If that doesn't work for you,
let the King lead and let all the Chiefs follow,
to go and kill this "mere thief".
Exactly!
Elders always say; “the depth of an elders knowledge…”
"is always hidden!"
How dare you say that?
Oguntade!
Yes Chief!
Don’t toy with our intelligence!
Are you trying to help or just mocking us?
Mock you? I dare not! Who am I to try such.
All I’m trying to say is we don’t want any troubles…
[Hunters singing]
We don't want trouble.
Then, the kingdom called out to Sango,
the god of Thunder and fire for help.
God of thunder and fire.
The palm and pawpaw trees bow to the wind.
When thunder strikes in the forest, all the inhabitants feel it.
Agesinkole has refused to honor you,
I hereby send death to him today! May he die a shameful death!
Sango!
Sango will never strike the house of a bata drummer
The blacksmith’s tweezer will never fail him
Neither a basket or a net can ever hold water
Sango...god of fire
Give me your power!
[Agesinkole group slang]
Sango the god of thunder,
you have not broken your covenant with me.
Death and sickness are not mates.
When death speaks, sickness is silent.
Boys...
Come and taste from the oil of Sango! It's very tasty!
Yes my Lord, we will all taste it.
well done everyone.
(Abegunde hailing himself)
Listen to this fool!
I've played.
Look here Abegunde, I already told you,
Ladele is the only one you can bully!
Who?
You are the only one he can bully.
Me?
Okay then,
did you not flee into the bush days ago when Agesinkole arrived?
Me?
Didn't you run?
Me? Run from someone like that!
You're a big liar.
What is your problem?
He is just an ant under my foot!
Really?
Let me tell you...
what?
I'm not just a masquerade, I have Charms too!
That's why my masquerade is celebrated.
Haven’t you heard how they praise my masquerade?
How?
They always starts with a mighty roar...
Lafongido..the powerful masquerade that
rips your arm apart with just one pull.
Look here, you will suffer!
Me? No way!
You will suffer a lot.
In two days, he is coming to take away all your harvest.
He dares not! What do you take me for? He would not try it.
What do you mean?
Someone like him?
Have taxes been paid to me, that I will then pay someone else?
Really?
Listen! If you want to be disgraced in the next two days...
Are you not close to the palace?
Yes.
Tell the Palace to call me.
Really?
Let me battle with him.
I promise you, he won't return in one piece!
Listen Abegunde, you brag too much.
Are you sure of what you're saying?
Yes!
Are you sure you are up to the task like your fathers?
Yes, I am confident.
If not, then you’re a bastard.
You are a bastard.
Wait here!
I cannot behave like a bastard.
Why would I be afraid of him? What does he have?
Will you play! I’ll deal with you!
[Gunshot]
What is it? Me?
I am a terrifying fire..a great storm on fields of wheat
Me?
You’re a man indeed! You are capable.
Why are you on the floor?
Even with your big size, you fell flat on the floor.
My King, why are you restless?
Why is your heart troubled everytime over a trivial matter?
Mobonuola
My King.
Are you unaware of the things happening in the village?
And you still ask why I am troubled? Why shouldn’t I?
Did you not hear the tale of Agesinkole's recent robbery?
When things like these happen, as the head,
I should have a confidante, but there is none!
There's no one I can discuss with.
And you who should be…
My King,
there is no one who would fail to answer your call.
When I called you a while ago, didn’t you respond?
Please stop beating around the bush.
I'm not a child.
My King, you are raising your voice.
I am not,
you are the one who has refused to listen to me!
We are saying different things.
Look here,
still on the question I have been asking,
I want an answer now.
Mobonuola
Are you a witch?
My King, let us not drag this issue.
Just come get something eat.
And on the issue of the robber disturbing the village...
it is sorted! He won’t come here again.
I am more than capable!
Greetings baba.
Welcome boys, may it be well with you.
Getting frustrated, the kingdom reached
out to the young warriors of the land.
One was named Abegunde.
Abegunde, at this juncture, what can we do?
This is about money. If you are ready to
pay for the sacrifice for my masquerade,
He will send me forth, and I will go face him.
Did you not say he is coming in two days?
I’ll capture and break him like a duck's egg
Really?
Oh yes!
Ok, what exactly do you want from us?
Yes, let’s get to business.
My masquerade will take seven barrels of Palm oil,
What?
seven big cockerels,
and a mature He-goat, with a substantial amount of money.
What? Abegunde! This is too much!
Didn't you say it was 'a little sacrifice'?
This sounds more like you’re planning a big festival.
Chief, why are you talking this way?
Don’t you know the task ahead is a huge one?
And the target is no ordinary man.
Really?
Whoever wants to challenge a strong
man must also be stronger.
That's true.
But what if we do all these and you are not successful?
Don’t doubt me
At this point, we have to question your capability
this is very crucial at this point,
what if you don’t get him?
I said do not doubt me
[Abegunde growls]
Lafongido..the powerful masquerade that rips your arm apart
with just one pull
Let me go face him!
Let us give him a trial
(Praise songs for Abegunde)
[Praises for Lafongido the masquerade]
Lafongido..the powerful masquerade that
rips your arm apart with just one pull
Fearless and loved by his people,
he sought out to be the hero they needed.
stand back.. I will now disappear
Stop there! Where do you think you’re going?
On my father’s land?
You’re parading with style...
like the land belongs to you, one more step and you’re dead!
[Agesinkole group slang]
What is wrong with you?Are you celebrating or mourning?
You think I’m here to play?
You! Today, I’ll show you who I am.
One will scream at the sting of a wasp
One will cry to the heavens at the sting of a spiritual bee
one sting can cause a sore...another can cause death
Their powers bring pain and suffering
Great Spirits ...Agesinkole has invoked your anger
Now that you have been provoked, strike him with your sting
[AGESINKOLE group slang]
Stop there!
come back here
we have been fortified
how dare you compare your powers with ours?
Termites can never eat through stone
be transformed
They have crossed the line, and they will see my anger.
I am not robbing anymore, I am ready for war!
If you all want to rob, feel free!
I’ll be back.
Welcome
Thank you
Help! Help! Help!
Fire dared me and I swallowed it
The Sun dared me and I blotted it out
You have all dared me and now you want to run,
where are your feeble legs?
But Agesinkole survived all the attacks,
and words of his power spread across into the land.
striking fear and terror to all who
heard tales of his exploits.
Help me! Help me!
Look at my children! I’m doomed!
Please open your eyes, please.
I am doomed! I've lost everything.
The whirlwind has taken everything from me.
Invoking the witches.
On what I was talking to you about…
I'll be back.
Why are you covering yourself with darkness?
Who sent you?
I am always vigilant,
where are you from?
What are you here for?
Nobody sent me, I sent myself!
That's the answer to your first question.
I am from where your evil arrows keep penetrating!
That's the answer to your second!
I am here to kill you.
That's the answer your third question.
And to answer to your fourth question; I am a witch.
And there are some things that even a witch would not dare do!
Keep quiet! Do you think I am here to trade words with you?
Look here, you have seen me today, you shall surely die!
Death and I have no such agreement. Even death is afraid of me.
Wow, you seem serious. Woman, look, you are beautiful,
I wouldn’t want to destroy your beauty.
Insanity! Confusion! Madness! and chaos, I call upon you today!
INCANTATIONS
I call upon death for you, not sickness!
Never!
a blacksmith will never handle molten iron
any such attempt will only lead to pain and suffering
i have now neutralized your powers
and I have made them mine
Neither death nor disease have any effect on me
My Lord, I heard the sound of a gunshot just now.
I killed a squirrel damaging my farm
Did you kill it completely?
No, I only shot the leg.
You should have killed it completely.
A dog should never challenge a tiger!
Let it serve as a warning to the people who sent her.
What happened?
My King
What happened to you?
Where did this injury come from?
Talk to me, what is this injury?
It’s not an injury.
Are you saying I’m blind? This looks like a gunshot wound!
Mobonuola?
My King, this is a mere scratch
What do you mean by that!
How did this happen? I heard you scream.
Where did it happen? where are you coming from?
INCANTATIONS
Let my blood, flesh and bones return to their normal states.
Wonders shall never end.
Abegunde went into battle, and never returned,
Agesinkole has refused to stop robbing us,
does this mean that Abegunde's gods didn’t go with him?
Why would they go with him?
Actions taken with deceit and lies never end well!
Why would Abegunde make himself the
spokesperson for all the other masquerades!
Whatever has happened to him served him right!
That is to say, Abegunde has done more than he can handle.
The masquerades turned their backs on him.
Haven't you heard? Never mess with the masquerades.
Let him stay there!
Really?
Yes.
When you go down that path, you’ll find yourself at the palace!
Thank you.
I have never seen this face.
That is to be expected, everyone knows you,
but you can only know a few.
I know you very well my King.
I am Ifagbure, the son of Ifagbayi, from Igbokiti
Let me ask to be sure, are you talking of the same Fagbayi
Yes my King, the same!
Then I greet the Ifa Oracle once again.
The Ifa Oracle greets you too.
Hope all is well
My king, he Oracle says there is
a serious crisis in the land.
My King, there is a way out.
Really?
You are right,
what then does the Oracle require of us.
The Oracle says we must consult Ogun, the god of iron
Ogun?
Yes, my king.
consult individually or collectively?
[INCANTATION]
(Ogun Worshippers Chanting)
Ogun as you have done in the past,
pave way for us in this village!
Amen
Pave a way for us.
May we prosper in this village!
Amen
May the troubles of Agesinkole come to an end.
May sorrows and death see us and flee
Amen
My people, this is the kolanut
Go ahead
Can I proceed?
Yes!
Now we can have individual Kolanut supplications.
Old man, be careful.
This is it, may your creator pave a way for you.
May you prosper.
Amen
Can I go ahead?
Go ahead
The Kolanut has spoken!
Oguntade.
Father
I was at the collective Ogun worship yesterday and my Kolanut spoke!
Your Kolanut spoke?
Yes it did.
It spoke about your wife Aríyíbí
Father is all well?
That is why I’m here,
I was told that we need to find a big deer,
and sacrifice it for your wife.
So this unhealthy jealousy does not
kill her, like it killed her mother.
Father, is it that serious?
Yes, very serious.
I was initially scared when I thought
about the possibility of finding a deer,
but felt better when I remembered, her husband is a hunter.
That is why I’m here to see you.
That's ok, may Ogun make it easy.
Amen.
So when are we supposed to do this sacrifice?
Well, they warned that it shouldn't be more than seven days
Really?
Seven days?
Yes, seven days! How do we go about it?
Ogun help me.
God will help us.
Father, I have some pressing business to attend to,
there are some people I hunt with and they are not even in this village,
when I leave, I’m likely to be away for a month.
Really? What do we do?
Let him go where he wants to go.
Let him do whatever pleases him.
Apparently, I do not matter.
If it were to be giving out free meat
he would jump into the hunting forest immediately.
He doesn’t care if I live or die.
but, nothing must happen to me,
if anything happens to me…
Will you keep quiet and get out of here! Get out!
Father says you should go back into the house.
(Whispering), if anything happens to me...
Will you beat me up? He said get into the house!
My father…
Please don’t mind her
Mind her? Never!
I apologise to you.
By the grace of the gods, I will find a deer.
[Greetings]
My mother.
My Prince…
Here you are, I have searched around for you.
I’m out here checking the new beads.
That’s fine. I want to visit the game house.
I thought to let you know.
Are you serious?
The rain storms because of the blind,
and the cloud gathers because of the deaf.
Are you totally blind and deaf to all
the chaos happening in the village?
Have you gone deaf to it all?
Mother, be rest assured, nothing will happen to me.
I see... I understand you...
Is this what you learn at the game house?
Courage?
It’s fine. But this is my order, if you must step out of this palace,
you must go with guards! You must never walk alone.
That’s fine mother.
Now tell your Heads that by this time next year...
[Agesinkole group slang]
[Gunshot]
When death speaks, sickness merely grumbles.
Look here, this tax you received,
you won’t be around to receive another.
So shall it be!
They thought I was dead and I pretended to be,
little did they know that I was preparing for the big strike!
And you! Tell your village head,
that the next time he brings his tax here and not to my palace,
there will be war! Leave!
[Agesinkole group slang]
My Lord, if we don’t send a message, they won’t know how serious we are,
I suggest we kill one of these to pay homage to you.
[Gunshot]
[Agesinkole group slang]
Leave the dead,
let the living carry up all the properties of the dead.
And you, find your way to our palace with everything!
So shall it be!
My Lord, if you would allow it, I want
us to shed a lot blood in this village today.
Let’s do it!
[Agesinkole group slang]
[Gunshots]
If you dare run.
Go into their houses.
If you dare shout!
The deadly birds are crying.
Stay there!
Oh mothers of the earth…
What sin have I committed?
You asked for a goat, and I gave it to you.
You requested for a big ram.
I gave you a big ram.
You asked for a hen,
I gave it to you.
Why then did you do this to me?
Adefimihan!!!
Shut up your mouth.
What Adefimihan are you calling on?
Call him out and let’s see him!
Call out Adefimihan and let's see him.
You this shameless and stupid woman.
You have ruined my life.
You looked at me and destroyed the only
reason I was not called an infertile man
This woman...
What did I tell you?
Didn't I warn you to make sure he doesn't go out?
Why did you let him go out?
My king, my king, how was I supposed to know?
Know what?
Did I know that Agesinkole would
return back into this village?
The village was calm and things had return to normal,
why would I need to keep hiding the Prince?
My king, remember that the Prince and
the commoner were born the same way…
Don’t you dare finish that statement
If you dare finish the statement you are in big trouble.
You have pleased yourself, right?
My King
Adefimihan, you have punished me!
Adefimihan!!!
Mothers of the earth, I have suffered.
I have been stripped naked!
Adefimihan!!!
Wizards in the house, I hail you.
Witches in the house, I greet you
I greet all the spirit beings.
Thank you.
I thank you all for killing my son.
Thank you for stripping me naked.
Thank you for making me a childless man!
Thank you for ruining my life.
Haven't I done everything you asked?
It turns out you are not reliable.
It turns out you are not to be trusted.
I regret all the times I spent with you.
In fact, I curse the day I met you all.
I am here to warn you, that the next time
you see me here, do whatever you want to me
You worthless bunch
What is it?
Shameless beings.
My life was destroyed right under your noses,
or are you all here to take my life too?
I ask again, what did you ask that I failed to give?
All you requested of me even when
they were inconvenient, I gave to you.
I worshiped and paid homage to you,
yet you have made my life unbearable.
If I had known how unreliable you were,
would I have spent my life believing in you!
I say it again, if you ever see me here again,
do with me whatever pleases you.
Ingrates!
Shame on you.
Shame!
Shame on you all.
I sense something.
Agesinkole, your end has come.
That's impossible.
Keep quiet, before whom are you bragging?
[Incantations]
We have come take away your clothes of
honor, I order you to strip yourself naked!
[Incantations]
Agesinkole, may the winds blow you to heaven!
You killed my men!
Let all swords go back to their sheaths
Let all powers return to their sources
Sit down!
He says we should sit, let’s see what he plans to do.
I see that you witches came prepared.
What have I even done to deserve that?
My fathers, the wizards? Why did
you bring a gun to a fist fight?
I know you all, even if you don't know me.
You are surprised.
I know the witches, the wizards and even the spirits!
Look here, I won’t let you leave.
You will go with me to our destination.
[Agesinkole group chant]
Oguntade, worried about losing his wife to the cold hands
of death, sought out the necessary sacrifice.
-You found one?
-Ogun did it.
Oguntade!
Yes father!
May it we well for you, thank you.
So shall it be father.
May you be greatly rewarded for this!
Father, I did it for myself
You did it for both of us
My only plea is that the gods accept our sacrifice
They will, in fact, they have
Amen
We already have what they asked for, put your mind at rest.
Thank you father. Let me hurry home to freshen up
Its fine, you may go. Thank you so much.
Let’s thank the Ogun.
Wait right there.
What is going on?
What have I done and why are
your guns pointed at me?
Seize his gun!
Seize my gun?
Ogunsakin what is going on?
We have nothing to say to you here,
when we get to the palace, you will explain yourself.
May Ogun not let me have no reason
to explain anything at the palace.
What do I have to explain? What did I do?
You will explain your thieving act on Alonge's farm!
Me! No way! May Ogun not let me steal!
Yes, it was you. I saw you clearly.
Hello!
Ogun please help me
Who is there!
…if that is the case, let me…
What do you have to say?
Please don’t do this to me…
please, let’s settle this amicably.
Agesinkole has taken over the witches,
the wizards and the spirits.
He fought and conquered them all.
He is unstoppable at this point
I wasn’t even aware that the Queen is a witch.
Will you shut your mouth!
Which Queen is a witch?
Queen Bonuola.
Shut your mouth!
If you’re not careful, I’ll ask the guards
to slice off your mouth with a knife.
Wait, let’s exercise some patience.
Keep her calm and
let her say whatever she has to say.
Go on, I’m listening.
May your mouth not be the end of you.
Still, what can we do at this point?
My King
Calm down. what’s going on? What’s his offense?
He stole and we want judgement!
Mobonuola…
My King
Stop it, why are you calling him?
Can’t you see he’s in distress?
I can see it.
Can you see what I’m seeing?
They said you have stolen from them.
Even if we can’t attend to all cases,
we will definitely make an exception for a thief like you.
Hunters, take him to the Chief's court,
we will judge his case there.
Your running mouth will be attended to.
I beg you, please, it was a mistake.
With the proclamation, Oguntade
was already a dead man walking.
Oh my, I'm in trouble. they sentenced
you to face the deadly criminal?
The unstoppable bringer of death
That same Agesinkole?
What about Agesinkole?
Look at her, the cause of everything.
I don’t understand what's happening, mother.
How would you understand? You won't
understand until you become a mother.
Oguntade.
Yes mother.
I may not know much but this belly is filled with tricks
Rather than mourn over my child, I would use the only option left for me.
Oguntade, come with me.
Leave my way.
Come with me.
For no one could defeat Agesinkole.
Not the witches, nor wizards.
But, will a mother's love safe the
poor hunter from certain death?
So, Oguntade was buried alive for seven days.
[Chanting]
-Welcom my son.
And on the seventh day, he was
recalled from the land of the dead.
newly born, powerful and
ready for the dire task ahead.
I can smell a human.
A rat does not visit a bird's nest
a bird does not visit a rat's hole.
It is me.
Death has come to visit you.
Today, is your last day on Earth.
Take him, tie him up!
Stay right there!
A hen does not mistakenly swallow fire…
both of you, fall down and die! Die!
[INCANTATION]
I have postponed my death
Why are you here?
I am here to arrest you.
If I hold you in my hands, your blood will dry up.
I have to arrest you, you will stop terrorizing my people.
Agesinkole be like a mountain and swallow him up!
The god of iron built his house with fire
witches build their houses with blood
If I can’t reach you, my gun will reach you.
[Agesinkole group slang]
Ageshinkole I command you to be in chains!
You are indeed a great warrior, I know that now.
Now you know.
May it not be well with your ancestors.
If you dare make any sound again...
Agesinkole no matter how powerful you are,
today I am taking you to my King’s palace!
Ogundabede where are you?
You, what are you still waiting for?
Ogun the god of Iron, send my gun to me now!
Thank you Ogun.
[Gunshot]
Ogun killed him for me!
And you, are you not human?
Oh land hearken to the sound of my voice
[Incantations]
I said it, I said he is not human.
Now that you’re gone, may you never be able to return.
Remain a spirit forever.
You, I see you running off,
just go and die in a bush.
…And you watching me over there, die peacefully. Die.
wait for me, you can’t escape, I’m coming with you.
Let the wind take me on a journey.
Agesinkole stop there!
[INCANTATION]
If the masquerade chases me and I flee,
it is not a sign of cowardice… I am only being careful.
Young man, do you really want to fight with me?
Yes I want to fight with you,
I will capture you and keep you here.
Yes I want to fight with you!
You want to fight with me?
Now fight with me if you can.
Fight!
I know you well, but you don't know me.
You and I belong to the same bloodline.
I am Adeoye. The grandfather of Adeyele.
The betrayal of the land brought me to this level.
The betrayal of the elders turned Abinbesu and I into monsters.
Please, I don’t want to fight anymore.
You are my father, I know you…
[Singing the praise of Agesinkole's lineage]
I heard of you, you are my great-grand father.
I am the son of Elesude.
Elesude the son of Onisade.
The grand father of Adegoroye.
I heard tales of how you and Adegoroye....
Please have mercy, my ancestor
Great one, your anger is justified, but please have mercy.
I heard all in the stories...My grandfather told me about you.
He heard the tales from his grandfather.
You are my great-grand father.
Please have mercy, I beg you.
Pardon me, pardon me my father.
Please my father, be merciful.
My husband…
What is wrong with you?
Did I ask for water?
Do I look like a camel that wants to drink to it’s death?
This is the guest who needs water.
Who?
I will never hail an unworthy man,
a man who lacks integrity home and abroad.
The gods love who the people love.
And he is the one who should be king.
Someone struggling to wear the
crown does not deserve to be king.
And you're asking me to give him water?
I will never waste my water on such.
Will you keep your mouth shut!
Chief, just leave her alone and
let’s settle the serious issue.
I can’t even explain how I got here,
stones, fruits and other things were thrown at me.
It seems Prince Adeoye has charmed everyone.
There is nothing like that, he hasn’t charmed anyone.
Our people are just ingrates,
despite how we bribed everyone, from the
kingmakers to all the chiefs and also the elders.
They all rejected the huge amounts of money
we gave them. He didn't charm them.
Will you keep quiet!
What are you talking about? Despite how much I spent!
Do you remember when your roof was
leaking and you were almost homeless,
I covered your shame.
And you,
Look here!
Prince, hold on we don’t need to look at anything,
anger does not solve anything but destroys all.
The moment you began shaking your index finger,
I knew you were angry.
If you can suggest what to do, we will do it.
Anger will totally destroy things.
You are right.
Listen, there is a way…
At this point what do you think can be done?
It is true the villagers wants you as king on your father's throne,
but the Oracle has refused.
Despite all our efforts, the oracles have disagreed.
What do you think we can do?
My chiefs, the ball is in your court.
Whatever you advice is what I will do,
all I want is to ascend my father’s throne.
Prince, you trust us that much?
Who else is there to trust?
He’s so wise. Such a wise man.
Chief, he has made a good point.
Yes, he does
We can’t just neglect him.
No we can’t…
We can't.
Good of you. You are really a great
man and you reek of royalty.
You spoke exactly like royalty.
I have an advise,
there is a herbalist friend of mine
in a neighboring village…
Should I be honest with you? There is a way out.
You were right.
Even though the journey to wealth is a rough one,
during divination, the oracle has revealed to me
the tale of Ogundabede, the King of Thieves.
Meaning the Prince has to steal to become a king.
Yes.
If the prince does not still...
The Oracle further explains that the
Prince has to steal a fertile goat.
As his first act of stealing?
Yes.
You will not become the king if you won't
steal a goat. The Oracle has spoken.
Priest? Steal? Ogundabede?
Yes my Prince
They hate thieves in our village. We don't steal.
He needs to steal.
Chiefs?
The road to greatness is filled with dirt,
you can’t reject the voice of the Oracle.
Meaning that the root of wealth is rotten!
Are you sure this is not a conspiracy?
If the Herbalist were to be from this village,
I would have thought the same but,
he is from a neighbouring village.
I also trust Chief Ọtun so well,
he will never deceive me.
That is true, he is the only Chief
who genuinely loves us.
Right.
If Chief Ọtun loves us,
then all other Chiefs have no
choice but to do the same
Yes.
The way forward is to steal.
You think I should steal?
Yes, if that’s the only way, you
can't go against destiny.
This could be your destiny and the
only way to ascend the throne.
Our soon-to-be King.
Have you forgotten that in three days,
the kingmakers will be at the
palace with the Ifa Oracle?
Where the final decision will be made
between you and the other prince.
Do you want to wait until you are ridiculed
by the Oracle to not become the king?
Chief Ọtun, I’m confused.
I have thought about it a great
deal and I am still confused.
…To steal a goat?
What if I’m caught?
In a town where we all know death
is the consequence of stealing.
since the days of our forefathers.
How will they know?
No one will know, they will only
know what we want them to know.
Really?
Chief, if I eventually take the goat…
-No, you won’t take it, you will steal it!
You have to steal,
that’s the idea, that is what the Oracle wants.
It's 'Ogundabede'.
If possible, talk to the goat. Let
it know you're about to steal it.
Don't you know that goats can hear us?
Goats can hear us.
You have to steal.
I will steal.
It is important to steal…
I will.
The poor prince did as was told by the corrupt
chiefs and a great horror befell him.
Well done, the shots scared me.
We didn’t shoot to scare you,
we are messengers from the palace.
How? See, the Chiefs are aware of this errand.
What chiefs? Open your bag.
The chiefs know about it
Take the bag from him and check!
The chiefs are aware,
The chiefs they know about this…
I’m dead, they are aware!
What! This goat belongs to Ayoka's mother.
Pick it up!
Like I said before, the Chiefs…
Carry the goat or I shoot you.
Please don’t shoot me.
Put it around your neck!
Now, like I was saying, the Chiefs know about this.
Please don’t shoot me.
This is beyond us,
our hands are completely tied.
For as much as we want you to live amongst us forever,
your actions and deeds will not allow it.
Oh dear, this is really tragic.
Iyalode, this is beyond sympathy.
Chiefs.
We cannot neglect our culture and tradition,
whoever does the unthinkable must face the consequence.
Look, this isn't personal,
but we can't be nonchalant
If we let you, you will sell this entire village and destroy it.
The Snake killer!
I'm here.
Do your work.
[Incantations]
I have brought the head of the
evil one, come for your meal.
Come forth!
Good job...
That is your meal…
My friend.
My friend Adeoye, what a pity.
Truth is dead, only deceit now lives.
Adeoye! Adeoye!
Adeoye please wake up,
Adeoye, you know people will ask me about you.
What do you want me to tell them?
What do I tell them when they ask, please wake up.
God please help me breathe life into him.
Adeoye! Adeoye!
What am I supposed to do now?
What a pity… I will do my duty to you as a friend,
I will give you a proper burial.
This is not your final resting place my friend.
My good friend Adeoye, what a pity.
What a pity!
[Gunshots]
We caught him!
If you move, I will shoot!
Please have mercy, I’m not moving.
-Get up.
-You want me to get up?
You caught him?
We did!
I heard the shots. Great job everyone.
Chief please have mercy on me.
So it is true? You came to harvest his head?
You were stealing together?
No we weren’t
You came to take his head! Take him away!
Move!
Please let me walk backwards…
No, you will walk forward.
Move!
Tell it to the world and everyone who
cares to listen that the world is evil.
They kill the good people with all their good intentions.
My ancestors, do not let my sufferings
be in vain. Rise up and save me.
With their souls seeking reincarnation,
Prince Adeoye and his friend were executed.
With their souls seeking revenge, the prince
reincarnated to become the king of Thieves.
And his friend became his trusted ally.
I did not just decide to become evil
but a great evil was done to me.
I did not just decide to revenge.
But every time I journey through the path where
your forefathers buried me,
It fuels my anger afresh.
I have waited for the son of Tadenikaro to become
king, so I can punnish him for his father's sin.
Your forefathers turned me into a tyrant,
your fathers created a monster.
You all know how to treat thieves,
but do you know what your forefathers stole from me?
It's more than stealing mere yams.
A pure case of the kettle calling the pot black!
All of you...
Oguntade!
My father, please have mercy on me.
[Singing the praise of Agesinkole]
What is my death worth to you?
I have made my decision and this is an order!
King!
A thief who steals food items is obviously hungry.
Feed such thief, before he dies of hunger.
Any man who steals out of greed,
caution him and pass the judgement with wisdom.
Think about your forefathers who destroyed the land,
and sold all your treasures, and left you wretched.
What have you done to them?
If you kill such, you have not acted wickedly.
Remove the log in your eyes, before
removing someone else's!
Where is the gourd in me?
I am leaving, I am going home.
If you don't want Agesinkole to return,
keep my commandments.
Keep my commandments!
[Oguntade singing a praise chant]
MOBONUOLA…
So, what happened to him after that?
He went away with the wind, and will come back
when and wherever injustice prevail.
Just as he promised.